# Siemen Burssens

Research Fellow, School of Computing, University of Leeds

Date of Birth: Jan. 9, 1995

Sheffield, United Kingdom

siemen.burssens@gmail.com

https://s-burssens.github.io

0000-0002-1593-0863

# Key Skills

Data analysis & visualisation

Statistical inference & modelling

Technical & professional writing

Presentation & communication

Project management Python

numpy/scipy/pandas/plotly/seaborn

Jupyter Notebook | SQL | Git/Github

### Personal

I'm interested in the extraction of knowledge from data sets and the delivery of insights for stakeholders of varied backgrounds or to inform policy design. With my experience as a researcher and a data scientist I know how to work efficiently and autonomously in order to meet deadlines and complete project goals in a timely manner. As a result, I have the ability to learn new concepts and methods quickly, and possess strong interpersonal and presentation skills.

## Interests -

Problem solving

Data visualisation

Machine learning

Sustainability and SMART cities

Astronomy and geophysics

### **Profiles**





### Education

2018 - 2022 **PhD** in Astronomy and Astrophysics

> Thesis title: Massive star asteroseismology with TESS and K2. Supervisors: Dr. Dominic M. Bowman, Prof. Dr. Conny Aerts

Degree obtained: 4 July 2022.

Link to thesis: https://tinyurl.com/3dbysvrv

2017 - 2018 M.Sc. in Medical Radiation Physics

Thesis title: Knowledge-based treatment planning: a RapidPlan ap-

Supervisors: Ir. Msc. Tom Depuydt

Grade: 2:1

2015 – 2017 M.Sc. in Astronomy and Astrophysics

KU Leuven, Belgium

KU Leuven, Belgium

KU Leuven, Belgium

Thesis title: Molecular analysis of oxygen-rich AGB-star V1300 Aql.

Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Leen Decin, Dr. Taissa Danilovich.

Grade: 1st

2012 - 2015 **Bachelors degree in Physics** 

KU Leuven, Belgium

with a minor in Biochemical Sciences

### Professional experience

### Key projects

 H20forAll: Increasing citizens' awareness and engagement regarding disinfection by-products and drinking water quality (2023-2024, University of Leeds).

My role in this EU Horizon project includes using data-driven evidence to increase public awareness about disinfection by-products and engage citizens to take actions that protect water quality now and in the future. To achieve this I'm taking a two-way approach: developing a model that allows citizens to calculate their exposure and pollution profiles, and conducting a social study to determine which actions are most readily adopted and lead to overall behavioural change.

Project management | Systematic literature reviews Social study design Survey data analysis Scientific modelling | Software: Python, R, QGIS

 MAMSIE/PARADISE: Statistical data modelling of neutron star progenitors (2020-2022, KU Leuven).

Here, I developed up a Python-based statistical modelling framework to derive physical properties of neutron star progenitors. This included extracting data from large astronomy databases and the analyses of multiple data sets of different sources. I also performed simulations of stellar structure and evolution using high performance computing, and conducted an in-depth statistical analysis using a variety of computational methods and algorithms.

The results of this research were published as a research article in the peer-reviewed scientific journal Nature Astronomy (doi:10.1038/s41550-023-01978-y) .

Time-series data | Multiphysics simulations | High performance computing Statistical inference Bayesian analyses Software: Python, SQL, Fortran

 MAMSIE/PARADISE: First scientific results of the novel TESS space mission telescope (2019-2020, KU Leuven).

In this project I set up a Python-based data processing framework to combine data sets of 98 stars from different telescopes, including data sets from the recently launched TESS space telescope. I then used the framework to deliver new evidence-backed insights into the evolution of stars more massive than our Sun.

Resulted in the publication of a research article in the peer-reviewed scientific journal Astronomy and Astrophysics (doi:10.1051/0004-6361/202037700).

Data extraction Time-series data Scientific computing Data visualisation High performance computing | Software: Python, SQL

## Languages

**Dutch** (Native language)

English (IELTS Band score 7.5)

French (10 years at Sec. school)

Italian (Resident for 10 years)

German (2 years at Sec. school)

Spanish (Intro classes A1)

#### Other relevant experience

 Four years of teaching experience in undergraduate university programs (2018-2022).

Assistant lecturer on courses in mechanics, electrodynamics, thermodynamics, and astronomy. My duties included the development of lesson plans, hands-on exercise sessions, mentoring students, and the design, supervision and correction of exams.

 Speaker and participant at several international conferences and seminars (2019-2022).

This included conferences organised by the European Astronomical Society (EAS, link), and the International Astronomical Union (IAU361, link). Here, I obtained hands-on experience with proper data visualisation, presentation skills, and public speaking in front of large audiences.

- Scientific outreach through a variety of channels (2019-2022)
- This included organising and participating in open science days at the university for young students aged 6 through 16, dedicated visits to local high schools, and writing online blogs and articles. Here, I advanced my communication and presentation skills by presenting complex topics to non-expert audiences in a comprehensive way.
- Experimental design and on-site observations with the Mercator telescope situated on the island of La Palma, Spain (2018-2022).

Principal investigator of HERMES observing programme 99, focused on the gathering of high-resolution spectroscopic data with the HERMES spectrograph mounted on the Mercator telescope (http://www.mercator.iac.es). Included two on-site solo observing runs of two weeks where I operated the telescope autonomously.

- Member of the international IACOB project (2019-2022).
   International collaborative project focused on the analysis and gathering of high-resolution spectroscopic data sets of massive stars in the Milky way.
   (http://research.iac.es/proyecto/iacob/).
- Member of the local organising committee of the TASC6/KASC13 Astronomy conference, Leuven, Belgium, 11-15 July 2022 (300 participants).

In this role I developed both organisational and managerial skills as part of a team.